[SPEAKER_01]: We did a little meditation on relative bodhicitta and now to focus and meditate a little bit on absolute bodhicitta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolute bodhicitta is meditating on I think we can say two natures of
[SPEAKER_01]: all the phenomena outer phenomena understanding resting and understanding of true nature of outer and inner outer phenomena and inner
[SPEAKER_01]: So there are also many different methods or different teachings about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So one way to do is to see everything, all the phenomena that appears to oneself as nothing but a dream or illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: all outer phenomena as well as all the sentient beings everything nothing but a dream nothing exists outside but everything projection of one's own mind so people who are quite familiar with Mahayana Sutras will understand
[SPEAKER_01]: how to meditate on emptiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also in Buddha's teaching like Heart Sutra and all that explains quite detailedly how to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: focusing detailedly, emphasize on emptiness, which actually I think talking about all phenomena is not real, but it is on mind projection, it's all like a dream, dream and illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So later, like great scholars like Nagarjuna explained more detailed
[SPEAKER_01]: way to how to analyze all the outer phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through analytic then we will find everything nothing but emptiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there are many different ways to do that also.
[SPEAKER_01]: the most elaborate ways to do that is the teaching of interdependent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is nothing but interdependent and everything is nothing but emptiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if we sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: look in quite a simple ways to look at things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next example.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we see, take an example of incense, a long incense and then the short incense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you see the long incense you will say this is long and this is a short incense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you bring even longer incense, incense stick, then that long incense becomes a short incense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you call it one is long and one is short because in relation.
[SPEAKER_01]: in relation, not in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So same thing, I think many things we label in outer world, good, bad, beautiful, not beautiful, pleasant, unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is mostly we label them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not exist independently.
[SPEAKER_01]: On is on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore, when you analyze like that, all very detailly, most of the things that we perceive, it does not exist by its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore, when you analyze through analyzing, some kind of understanding,
[SPEAKER_01]: all the phenomena and nothing but its own kind of mind projection.
[SPEAKER_01]: So trying to rest in this kind of state of mind and then also we can look back into our mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it really there is something called mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: then the past thoughts, future thoughts, present thoughts, and if past and present meet, it becomes present.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the future thoughts and present thoughts meet, it becomes future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So therefore if you analyze stream of mind, you will also not find such thing as solid entity as a mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when we meditate,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's two kinds of meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is what we call analytic, analyzing all the outer phenomena, analyzing all the inner state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through investigating and analyzing, you will reach to a certain kind of understanding or certain kind of small experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then trying to rest without fabricating
[SPEAKER_01]: just sort of remain in that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's called what we call ultimate bodhicitta because how this is the how all outer and inner absolute truth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's kind of brief introduction on how to sort of rest
[SPEAKER_01]: state in meditation of Absolute Bodhicitta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to actually put in practice what Rinpoche explained on the Absolute Bodhicitta, as Rinpoche mentioned, first we go to an analytical process, taking first out of phenomena,
[SPEAKER_00]: She gave the example of the notion of short and long, which doesn't exist in themselves, they're just relative.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even anything that we take on its own, like a table.
[SPEAKER_00]: If we break it into pieces, just pieces of wood, it's no more what we call a table.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even a piece of wood, we may put it into sawdust, it's just wood dust.
[SPEAKER_00]: molecules and atoms and particles and whatever quacks or superstring or quantum vacuum anyway at the end certainly not a table so likewise it is the case of all phenomena and then we come at a point where we can see that is everything is just but labels attached to certain things that comes momentarily together but do not constitute separate entities
[SPEAKER_00]: So therefore, there's no object of grasping either.
[SPEAKER_00]: We cling to a beautiful sort of, I don't know, Ming Dynasty Chinese table, but not to a heap of sawdust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless we're a sawdust dealer, then it becomes expensive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Valuable for us.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, what is a sawdust dealer?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is something for a sawdust dealer, just an annoying heap of sawdust for someone who finds that in his flat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or like a roses is very...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a wonderful thing for a poet.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a good salad for a snail.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's nothing much for a tiger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So likewise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now if you look at the mind, as Rinpoche said, we might think that the mind is something because we do experience it all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as Rinpoche mentioned, the past thoughts are gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: The future thoughts are not born yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: The present is...
[SPEAKER_00]: never staying in the same place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So where is this mind hanging out between something that does not exist anymore, that does not exist yet and can't grasp it in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So though there is undeniably some experience, it's not something that we can cast, that we can point out and say, this is the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a separate entity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is analytical meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And which leads us to the ultimate nature of thing is what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet it appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how does it appear?
[SPEAKER_00]: As something that is devoid of intrinsic existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we do not fall neither into nihilism, things that don't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course they do appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how do they appear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not as something solid, realistic, materialistic.
[SPEAKER_00]: It appears that it is void.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that union of appearance and emptiness is said to be the ultimate view according to the Madhyamika and especially in the Nyingma philosophy, view of the Madhyamika.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then we go through this analytical process until we achieve some kind of clarity and certainty like Chancellor Moshe used to say if we think that there's a thief somewhere in the house and we don't feel easy about that
[SPEAKER_00]: and then maybe I'm just daydreaming, so we look everywhere, open every cupboard, look under every bed, and then when we don't find any teeth, then our mind is at rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when we go pursue that in the end, and then we find nothing, and that's when times come for the second aspect that Rinpoche mentioned, that is the contemplative aspect, we gain a kind of clarity,
[SPEAKER_00]: almost like a certainty or at least for the time being we got some certainty compared to before now we need to let that soak in in a way and that the best way is not to pursue the analysis but just to rest in that understanding just like letting it soak in
[SPEAKER_00]: by leaving time, giving it time without further sort of intellectual elaborations so we can try to do that a little bit either taking the example of outer phenomena or taking example of the mind or taking example of the individual self that we cannot find either and if you want to do
[SPEAKER_00]: give the analytical way about the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: We think it's me somewhere, but where?
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly not somewhere in the body, my knees or my heart.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it diffused throughout the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can't say that because if we lose our legs, it's still me without legs, but it's not half of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just my body is diminished, but my me is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not outside me.
[SPEAKER_00]: so if it's not in the body then where?
[SPEAKER_00]: maybe in the consciousness and then same reasoning like for the mind is the me in the past in the future that is not born now that we cannot catch so basically we don't find it and then also this notion of me is very often illogical sometimes we say if I push your body you say oh you push me so then you think you identify me with the body and at that moment
[SPEAKER_00]: I say something unpleasant to you, you say you hurt my feelings so now me is my feeling, you hurt me so sometimes it's the mind, sometimes it's the body so that shows that it's neither in any of those so then we can use that analytical either for phenomena or for the mind or for the notion of self and then when we come to a point where we don't find any entity we just rest into that and contemplate this nature
[SPEAKER_00]: of things, of phenomena, of the mind, of the self, which appears yet is devoid of altruistic existence, and try to just rest into that understanding for a few moments.
[SPEAKER_00]: If we think of that, that point of resting is also the same point that is behind the screen of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: When past thoughts have ceased for a moment, we are not yet invaded by future thoughts, and there's a kind of freshness in that present moment, a kind of clear awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the same quality
[SPEAKER_00]: in which we can rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: In some texts it's called the simplicity, the natural simplicity of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a bit like when we have been carrying a heavy load and working in the mountains and at some point we put everything down and sit in front of a big landscape and there's a kind of sudden sort of letting go with not much thought, no hopes, no fear and then just resting
[SPEAKER_00]: in this state of natural simplicity.
[SPEAKER_00]: so what do we do when this state of freshness and resting in the present moment is disturbed by thoughts there's no much point even thinking of stopping them doesn't make sense even because how can you stop something that's already there so you can't prevent it from arising a thought that's already arisen
[SPEAKER_00]: So when they have not a reason, it's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they have a reason, they are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So stopping the thoughts makes no sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what do you do when they have a reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: So most of the time, in ordinary times, we get carried out by our thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they multiply.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they give a kind of chain reaction and invade our mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how we are constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: like under the sway of discursive thoughts but you can as well if you are mindful enough see the thought arising and just let it pass like you let something pass in front of you or like a bird that passes through the sky and doesn't leave any trace so then it's fine
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could that once, and twice, and many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not really difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all we have to do is to let it come, let it go, and let it vanish.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we can say it's hardship.
[SPEAKER_00]: So let's try to do that for a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: and then if we get used to that then we never lose the recognition that the sky is always there I mentioned like a bird passing through the sky but instead of being sort of obsessed or focused by the bird and seeing nothing but the bird if you see the bird passing through the sky then one bird, two birds, three birds
[SPEAKER_00]: you still see the sky very clearly even birds pass through so therefore the sky is not disturbed it's always you never lose sight of the sky and never distracted by the birds so that's a way to rest in absolute bodhicitta
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, how to connect the two bodhicittas?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if within that resting in the state of mind, then the perception and the thought of sentient beings comes, and then you realize that because of failing to understand the Absolute Nature, because they grasp and we grasp
[SPEAKER_00]: to solid reality, to the notion of a separate self, to the notion of beautiful and ugly, pleasant and unpleasant, friend and enemy, being endlessly suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, because of that understanding of Absolute Bodhichitta, then your compassion for the root cause of suffering, not just again the headaches and so forth, or the even dramatic
[SPEAKER_00]: violence and so forth but for the deep cause of ignorance and lack of awareness then very even more powerful compassion will arise for each and every of those sentient beings so the understanding of the Absolute Bodhisattva given altogether greater dimension and depth of two relative Bodhisattva that is to wishing that every being
[SPEAKER_00]: maybe free from suffering, because now you have a better insight about what is the ultimate cause of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So your compassion grows even faster, because it's grounded in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So in that way, one proceeds from the other, out of absolute bodhicitta, boundless compassion arises, it applies to all sentient beings, and we can train it further through the different methods of mind training.
[SPEAKER_00]: of the relative body citta so let's try to reflect a few moments upon how those two can be thus combined
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, this being the two main aspects, absolute and relative bodhicitta, in the
[SPEAKER_00]: In daily practice there is also many different kinds of meditation methods and visualization which can help day after day to enhance those and bring progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there are sort of additional instructions in order to amplify our
[SPEAKER_00]: compassion and bodhichitta and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So one of them which is very much practiced especially in Tibetan Buddhism is called the supreme exchange of giving one's happiness and taking upon ourselves others' suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it happens that some people are a little bit
[SPEAKER_00]: sort of feel strange about this way I even heard I saw once a description of supposed to be a psychological sort of visualization where people say well when you feel a lot of suffering and difficulties and so forth and
[SPEAKER_00]: and tormented within yourself and your physical suffering just imagine that you gather all of them like a sort of like something like tangible thing and suddenly with your breath you expel everything out to the world thank you very much for sending us all that so here is clearly the opposite instead of sending all our trouble outside and tell people just deal with that
[SPEAKER_00]: we do the opposite, but in a way that is not what people might fear, which is to increase our own burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another reaction is, how can I ever conceive of taking suffering of others?
[SPEAKER_00]: I have enough on my plate.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't even deal with my own difficulties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you want me again to sacrifice myself and take everything on me?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can that work?
[SPEAKER_00]: But all that comes from a very self-centered perception of
[SPEAKER_00]: suffering of others' suffering and one's own suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's self-centered perception that is usually the cause of your own suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if you take it from an altruistic perspective, then there's nothing about being discouraged, overburdened, overwhelmed, this feeling that it's not your job and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's unboundless courage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that boundless courage is actually a positive quality that
[SPEAKER_00]: lift up actually your strength and your spirit other than discouraging you and also that if you assume other suffering in certain way it's not at all a burden it's a joy and also because you can transform it so how does that practice goes well when we we first visualize all the manifold suffering of sentient beings
[SPEAKER_00]: and then when we think that when we breathe in through the nose usually but whatever it's like we are kind of extracting those suffering out of sentient beings and to give it a more sort of dramatic aspect we think it's like a dark smoke or some kind of dark sort of string that comes to us little bit like when there's a wind sort of movement
[SPEAKER_00]: that the smoke is moves towards you and comes in your nostrils and gathered in your heart but there you visualize your heart as a bright mass of white light and all those sufferings sort of dissolve so they are not burdening you they just transform then when you breathe out having taken and just
[SPEAKER_00]: taken away the suffering from all beings not only the suffering but the causes of suffering all the negative emotions and everything then you send out everything positive that you have all your merit your happiness your capacity or whatever good you did you send that to all beings and each of them receive it fully it's not like you
[SPEAKER_00]: chop a piece of cakes into one million tiny pieces but every being gets the whole thing and then you do this again and again thinking of the different kinds of beings the different kinds of suffering bringing out gathering their suffering it sort of transforms completely into emptiness and then you send out your happiness and do so again and again with great joy
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the practice of giving and taking and so we can do that for a few moments and then I will say a few words about the last variant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this we can do at any time and also when we do encounter suffering say we are sick or we have a strong pain or we have a strong sadness we can do the same as thinking that oh in the same way that I am sad or that I am in pain there are so many beings who have the same pain even sometimes much harder than mine so may
[SPEAKER_00]: when we do the breathing in may I take away all those sufferings similar to mine add it to mine but strangely enough the fact to add it instead of adding to our burden relieves it because there's a sense of giving it meaning imbuing it with compassion so it actually does seem much lighter to bear and it's not at all increasing our suffering but imbuing it with compassion because
[SPEAKER_00]: We think it stands for others' suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another way to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the final way, which is also found in the scriptures, is to do the same with mental suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means if people are taken by anger or jealousy, and so to, in the same way, when we're breathing, remove this mental poison from sentient beings, taking upon us
[SPEAKER_00]: transforming it, and sending out the opposite, like loving-kindness if we've taken out anger, rejoicing if we took out jealousy, and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the thing we can do at all times, whatever we do in our activities, when we walk, when we sit somewhere, we can think of that exchange.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now to conclude, before Rinpoche gives blessing to those who want to come and receive his blessing, we do the dedication.
[SPEAKER_00]: And before Rinpoche recites the verses of dedication, the dedication is considered to be like the seal, like when we put at the end of a long discussion, we put a seal of agreement, something that makes it final and solid.
[SPEAKER_00]: So here the reason why we dedicate
[SPEAKER_00]: is to ensure that the benefit of what we have done will continue, will live longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: We say that if we just do a session like today, and we just get up and think of something else, the results are very transient.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like we say the cactus flower, it flourishes once every many years, and then as soon
[SPEAKER_00]: soon after the cactus has flourished, has bloomed, it dies or it is like a snowflake falling on hot stone, it evaporates right away but if we say, oh may all the merit accrued by this few hours we spent together trying to practice and understand the compassion and loving kindness and the way to engage in that meditation
[SPEAKER_00]: May that in the moment, it alleviates all kinds of present suffering of sentient beings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the long term, may it serve so that those beings can attain enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it's like a snowflake falling in a big lake.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will somehow remain as long as the lake remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that merit will remain as long as we achieve enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So may, let's dedicate that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fr.
[SPEAKER_00]: Moshe will say the verses of dedication and then for a few seconds we will visualize thus dedicating all the merit for the short and the long term benefit of sentient beings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sanam Diyetam Jisivanyetone Nivetanam Vamjit Jigvanam Jigvalam Sivetsoletavatravaishu Sanjurimbhojitmakyepanam Jigyurjitmibayankhondegontupervarashu
[SPEAKER_01]: The first question is regarding the meditation of the four immeasurables that was taught earlier on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it by repeating each immeasurable by sequence or by visualizing a scene?
[SPEAKER_00]: So the sentences are beneficial, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: The classical one is may all beings find happiness on the cause of happiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: May all beings be free from suffering on the cause of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: May all beings...
[SPEAKER_00]: keep their happiness and that increase further and may this apply equally to all sentient beings without distinction so there's a prayer in Tibetan I don't know there's certainly equivalence in the Chinese in proper English and in Pali or whatever but this is just the to set the right understanding
[SPEAKER_00]: as well as the direction of the meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what really matters is the visualization and the actual practice that we do to integrate that so that it leads to a change of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what really matters is the actual practice based on visualization, based on understanding, based on integrating the meaning of those four.
[SPEAKER_01]: The next question is on the fourth measurable, which is impartiality.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the Dharma brothers has commented that this is a very difficult practice, especially for people you don't have empathy for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how do you interpret the attitude of impartiality and compassion?
[SPEAKER_00]: So I think that it's nothing difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a misconception between liking and loving.
[SPEAKER_00]: We don't ask you to like a dictator.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody likes a dictator.
[SPEAKER_00]: But loving a dictator is not also like just approving what he does.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is wishing with compassion that the root cause what makes that person a dictator, which is hatred, cruelty, indifference, and whatever, or greed, may that disappear from that person's mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's adopting the
[SPEAKER_00]: attitude of a doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if a doctor, I know there's some psychiatrists among us, if a very sort of little bit disturbed person comes and is a bit violent, so will the doctor say, it's very difficult for me, I want to take a stick and beat the patient down on the head?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, basically, it's not the proper reaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the doctor will do is to contain the patient if it's too violent and then find the right treatment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the more the patient is sick, the more the treatment should be appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like to say, I want to become a doctor, but I only want to try to treat benign sickness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too difficult to think about serious sickness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I don't think it's the case of doctors, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Venerable, if it's difficult, you don't have to look at me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't even look at you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I like to look at you because you ask me the question.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know who asked the question, so I'll look.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so the next two questions, I'll combine them because they're kind of related.
[SPEAKER_01]: One person asked how to overcome restlessness in meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another one asked how to overcome the taji and sleepiness in meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think there is some explanation, some experience we experienced during the meditation not to be attached to feeling of kind of bliss or feeling of samvara, clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Infinite.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not to cling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also if you feel, I think the question was feeling dull or a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also you sort of push up a little bit and then you can sort of start gazing upwards a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because before I mentioned
[SPEAKER_01]: put our eyes little bit down to his nose level but if you feel little bit sort of sleepy or or sort of cause the tibba yes, sinking sinking then you can for a moment you can sort of start gazing up little bit and gazing little bit further so what other one?
[SPEAKER_00]: restlessness so again
[SPEAKER_01]: putting down a little bit, focusing a little bit down and relaxing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I saw a sign in America somewhere, advertisement for peanuts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, relax and go nuts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can sort of relax and song compassion and go nuts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So again, these two questions are related.
[SPEAKER_01]: One said, I know I should meditate daily, but then I'm making excuses and not meditating.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I overcome that?
[SPEAKER_01]: This is related to another question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's difficult to implement meditation into daily life.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are your suggestions?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Making excuses and how to incorporate meditation into daily life.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think meditation
[SPEAKER_01]: just now we most of the people we do like physical exercise most people do like 45 minutes a day so meditation is a mental exercise so if you find a 45 minutes physical exercise people manage to integrate into their life so maybe you can find 20 minutes somewhere to integrate in your to mental exercise
[SPEAKER_00]: so yes if we do that then you know because when we do something like physical exercises because we see the benefit of it we have experienced it we are convinced that there is because we saw some evidence in scientific research or something else so we say oh that's beneficial so I'm ready to do that otherwise why would you be motivated so likewise if because of the past experience of your own experience of those described by the past teachers
[SPEAKER_00]: or those possibly described by scientific research you know about the benefit of say compassion meditation or mindfulness meditation and then it seems worth allocating that part of your precious time rather than many other things that in the end they're still 24 hours so the 24 hours they're just you know there's certainly certain use that you make of it and this is not
[SPEAKER_00]: completely a matter of choice if you have some obligations but there is still a margin of choice among the few hours of leisure time that you have so it's the enthusiasm to do something comes from contemplating the benefit of it so in particular if say 20 minutes or half an hour a day this really has a benefit not only for the moment where you do it but for the rest of the day and sometimes even the quality of your sleeps or whatever
[SPEAKER_00]: And then this is something very sort of valuable and you can appreciate that enough that you spend your time doing so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's a matter of how much you expect some benefit, how much you value those benefits compared to the consequences of what else you could do instead.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is the last question.
[SPEAKER_01]: I leave the best for the last.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the most difficult question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe to observe and control the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So exactly what or who observes and moves the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Observes the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe to observe and control the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what or who observes and moves the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: This is difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same time, same suit I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: so it's not such a difficult question the mind looks at itself what's the problem so well if you give an image you maybe understand better a light is needed to light up something else right but a light doesn't need a second light to a light itself because it's luminous
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind doesn't need another mind to look at itself because it has this faculty of knowing that it is imbued just as the light of a flame doesn't need a second life to be lighted up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's lighted by light.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I assume that you asked the question, so I'm really happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anyway, I already gave the answer, so thank you for the question.